Guide to the American Student Health Association Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
American Student Health Association records
1921-1939
SC0146
American Student Health Association
4 Linear feet
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer
Stanford University. Department of Athletics, Physical Education and Recreation
Stanford, California
Information about Access
None.
Historical Note:
The American Student Health Association was founded in 1921 by Drs. Warren E. Forsythe, John Sundwall, and others to provide an organization in which institutions of higher learning and interested individuals might work together to promote student health. Thomas A. Storey, director of Stanford's Student Health Service for many years, was closely involved in the early work of the association.
The Student Health Services of this period attracted creative young physicians, women and men, who were anxious to develop new approaches to the practice of medicine. The first attempts at group health plans in the United States grew out of student health work. The A. S. H. A. involved iself in this effort to ensure that all students -regardless of financial status -received first-rate medical care. The A. S. H. A. promoted a "positive health" approach to medicine, which saw its primary purpose as treating the sick.
Growth of the organization led to the creation of regional sub-sections in the late 1920s. Subsequent to the time period covered in this collection, the A. S. H. A. changed its name to the American College Health Association.
Scope and Contents Note:
This collection contains the files and proceedings of the American Student Health Association from 1921 through 1939. Included are materials pertaining to the annual meetings, bulletins and annual reports from the Health Services of the member schools, correspondence with member schools and regional sub-sections, journal articles, general correspondence, and administrative records.
Access Terms
American College Health Association..; Stanford University. Health Service.; Storey, Thomas A., (Thomas Andrew), 1875-1943.; Annual reports.; Students--Health and hygiene.
Collection Contents
- Correspondence and proceedings of the annual meetings of the A.S.H.A. from 1925 to 1930 (Box 1)
- Materials from the annual meetings of 1938 and 1939 (Box 2)
  The bulk of the material in this box is annual reports and bulletins of the Health Services of the member schools, and miscellaneous journal articles.
- Correspondence with member schools from 1937 to 1939, organized alphabetically by state; and correspondence and reports of annual meetings of the various regional sections of the A.S.H.A. (Box 3)
- Records for 1939 of the regional sections of the A.S.H.A. (Box 4)
- American Association of School Physicians, 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 1)
- American Medical Association Exhibit (Box 5, Folder 2)
- American Physical Education Association, 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Applications for Positions in Student Health Work, 1931-34 (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Applications for Positions, Men, 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Applications for Positions, Women, 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Bradshaw, R.W (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Committees -- General, 1920s-1930s (Box 5, Folder 8)
- Correspondence -- 1922-25 (Box 5, Folder 9)
- Correspondence -- 1922-25 (Box 5, Folder 10)
- Correspondence -- 1922-25 (Box 5, Folder 11)
- Correspondence -- 1922-25 (Box 5, Folder 12)
- Correspondence -- 1922-25 (Box 5, Folder 13)
- Correspondence -- 1926, 1929, 1930s (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Correspondence -- 1926, 1929, 1930s (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Correspondence -- 1926, 1929, 1930s (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Diehl, H.S. (Box 6, Folder 4)
- Docket (Box 6, Folder 5)
- Editorial Committee, 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Edwards, J.F. (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Executive Committee, 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Expenses, Other, 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Eye Health, 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 10)
- Forsythe, Warren E. (Box 6, Folder 11)
- Forsythe, Warren E. (Box 6, Folder 12)
- Health Problems of College Women, 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 13)
- Health Service, 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 14)
- Historical Material, 1920s-1930s (Box 6, Folder 15)
- Hygiene of Physical Activity, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Informational Hygiene, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 2)
- Inquiries, Non-members, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 3)
- Journal -- Lancet (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Lists, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 5)
- Mental Hygiene, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 6)
- Miscellaneous, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 7)
- Nomenclature, Study on (Box 7, Folder 8)
- Organization and Administration, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 9)
- Policy, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 10)
- Positions to be filled, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 11)
- President (Box 7, Folder 12)
- Program, 1920s-1930s (Box 7, Folder 13)
- Program, 1920s-1930s (Box 8, Folder 1)
- Prospects, 1920s-1930s (Box 8, Folder 2)
- Publications (Box 8, Folder 3)
- Raycroft, Joseph (Box 8, Folder 4)
- Round Table Suggestions (Box 8, Folder 5)
- School Health Education, Conference on (Box 8, Folder 6)
- Social Hygiene, 1920s-1930s (Box 8, Folder 7)
- Special Reports, 1920s-1930s (Box 8, Folder 8)
- Smiley, D.F. (Box 8, Folder 9)
- Storey, Thomas A. (Box 8, Folder 10)
- Surveys of Student Health Services, 1920s-1930s (Box 8, Folder 11)
- Training Personnel, 1920s-1930s (Box 8, Folder 12)
- Tuberculosis, 1920s-1930s (Box 8, Folder 13)